[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>(a) Explain the term Government as an art of governing.</p><p>(b) Why is Government important as an art of governing</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Government as an art of governing is the process of carrying out the day to day administration of the affairs a State which involves making, enforcing and interpreting laws.</p><p>(b)(1) Government provides external security throe. the armed forces.</p><p>(ii) It uses the judiciary to promote and maintain justice through the Courts.</p><p>(iii) Government provides social amenities e.g. water, electricity, schools, roads, libraries, hospitals, housing, etc</p><p>(iv) Government promotes economic development e.g. providing infrastructural facilities, enabling environment, etc.</p><p>(v) Government maintains law and order through the police force, immigration department, Customs and Excise department, etc.</p><p>(vi) It enacts laws to promotes good governance.</p><p>(vii) Government maintains external relations with other nations.</p><p>(viii) Government guarantees the Fundamental Human Rights of its citizens. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>Identify six external limitations to the exercise of sovereignty of the State.</p>",
        "answer": "<p> (I) International Laws and Conventions.</p><p>(ii) International Treaties and Agreements.</p><p>(iii) Dominance of powerful States.</p><p>(iv) Membership of International organizations e.g. UNO, OAU, (AU), etc.</p><p>(v) More economically advanced countries sometimes influence the exercise of sovereignty of poor countries.</p><p>(vi) External trade.</p><p>(vii) Diplomatic immunity.</p><p>(viii) Geographical location e.g. land locked countries, nearness to other States.</p><p>(ix) External Aids</p><p>(x) Inter dependence of States.</p><p>(xi) Religion and culture. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>(a) Define Fundamental Human rights.</p><p>(b) Highlight five means of safeguarding Fundamental Human Rights it State.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> Fundamental Human Rights are inalienable freedoms and privileges that individuals are entitled to in a State e.g. right to life, right to fair hearing, right to freedom of movement, etc.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) Entrenchment of Fundamental Human Rights in the State's constitution.</p><p>(ii) Existence of an impartial, free and independent judiciary.</p><p>(iii) Enactment of laws that protect the rights of individuals.</p><p>(iv) The existence of a free and independent media.</p><p>(v) Citizens must be educated to be able to defend their rights.</p><p>(vi) Public opinion must be effectively used to protect any violation of the rights of the citizens.</p><p>(vii) Existence of institutions such as the Ombudsman and the Public Complains Commission.</p><p>(viii) Respect for the rule of law.</p><p>(ix) Respect for international laws and conventions.</p><p>(ix) Provision of free legal aid.</p><p>(xi) Adherence to the doctrine of Separation of Powers and Checks and Balances.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>Identify six features of a parliamentary system of government.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) There is fusion of powers as members of the executive are also members of the legislature</p><p>(ii) The Head of State is different from the Head of Government.</p><p>(iii) The Prime Minister appoints ministers from within the legislature.</p><p>(iii) The Head of government is appointed by the Head of State, usually the leader of the majority party after a general election.</p><p>(v) There is Supremacy of Parliament e.g. Britain.</p><p>(vi) The government can be removed on a vote of no confidence by parliament at any time.</p><p>(vii) There is provision for an official opposition with an opposition leader.</p><p>(viii) Cross carpeting is allowed.</p><p>(ix) There is strict party allegiance and discipline.</p><p>(x) There is collective responsibility of the cabinet to the parliament.</p><p>(xi) In a bicameral parliament, all bills are first introduced in the lower house.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is Local Government?</p><p>(b) Highlight five sources of Local Government revenue. </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Local government is a semi-autonomous body created by law to provide the needs of the people at the grassroots level.</p><p>(b)(i) Grants from central government.</p><p>(ii) Statutory Allocation e.g. Nigeria from the Federation Account.</p><p>(iii) Rates/levies: There are rates people pay to maintain, sustain and expand social services.</p><p>(iv) State allocation: In Nigeria, at least 10% of internally generated revenue of the State Government.</p><p>(v) Investment in business yields to the local government.</p><p>(vi) Fees from liquor licenses, registrations, markets, motor parks, etc.</p><p>(vii) Court fines: (Share of court fines in Nigeria).</p><p>(viii) Donations and Gifts from NGO's, citizens, etc.</p><p>(ix) Royalties from companies in (Ghana, Sierra Leone and The Gambia). <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>Discuss six features of the traditional Yoruba political system.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) The system was based on constitutional monarchy.</p><p>(ii) The existence of a Council of Senior Chiefs.</p><p>(iii) There was an informal system of taxation e.g. tributes were paid in form of labour, yam, kolanut and animals by subordinate towns to their paramount ruler.</p><p>(iv) There was a system of checks and balances within the political system.</p><p>(v) There was the Oba as the paramount ruler.</p><p>(vi) The Oba and his Senior Chiefs met regularly to discuss issues that would promote peace, success and good governance.</p><p>(vii) Existence of secret societies e.g. Ogboni</p><p> (viii) Existence of a standing army headed by Are-onakakanfo.</p><p>(ix) Existence of chief priest.</p><p>(x) There was a process of law making, execution and adjudication.</p><p>(xi) Existence of king makers e.g. Oyomesi</p><p>(xii) Rulership was hereditary. No fixed tenure of office (for life). <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>Describe six factors that led to the growth of nationalism in Nigeria before 1945.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>The six factors that led to the growth of nationalism in Nigeria before 1945 are:                                                                                                   </strong></em>(i)The formation of political parties e.g. Nigeria National Democratic Party (NNDP) in 1923, Nigerian Youth Movement in 1934 and N.C.N.C. in 1944.</p><p>(ii) The establishment of local press and newspapers contributed to the spread of nationalists movement in Nigeria e.g. West African Pilot, Daily News, Daily Times. The Comet, etc.</p><p>(iii) The formation of the West African Students' Union (WASU) in 1925.</p><p>(iv) The formation of youth movements helped the growth and spread of nationalism in Nigeria e.g. LYM.</p><p>(v) The National Congress of British West Africa (NCBWA) was founded in 1919 and was led by Joseph Casely Hayford. It was established for the purpose of redressing the evils of the Crown Colony system.</p><p>(vi) The Atlantic Charter of 1941 which emphasized the right of people to self determination.</p><p>(vii) Racial discrimination against Nigerians by the colonialists e.g. European Club, European hospitals, etc.</p><p>(viii) The colonial policy of indirect rule excluded the educated elite from governance.</p><p>(ix) influence of Western Education on the people of Nigeria.</p><p>(x) Activities of the Trade Unions e.g. Nigeria civil service union 1921, NUT 1931, etc.</p><p>(xi) Rise of urban centres.</p><p>(xii) Appointment and deposition of chiefs by the colonial masters. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>Highlight six merits of the Richards Constitution of 1946 in Nigeria.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Merits of the Richards Constitution of 1946 in Nigeria are:</strong></em>                                                                                                                                      (i)The Constitution increased Nigerian representation on the Legislative Council.</p><p>(ii) It provided a link between the Native Administration and the Central Legislative Council through the Regional Assemblies.</p><p>(iii) It brought the North and South, for the first time, into one Legislative Council.</p><p>(iv) It provided for unofficial majority in the Legislative Council.</p><p>(v) The Constitution served as a stimulant for the development of nationalist activities.</p><p>(vi) It introduced bicameral legislature in Northern Nigeria.</p><p>(vii) It laid the foundation for the establishment of federalism in Nigeria.</p><p>(viii) Franchise qualification was reduced from one hundred pounds to fifty pounds annual income and 24 months to 12 months residence.</p><p>(ix) The Constitution provided for one Nigerian member in the Executive Council. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>(a) State the aims and objectives of the Unity Party of Nigeria (UPN).</p><p>(b) Outline four achievements of the part</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The aims and objectives of the Unity Party of Nigeria are:</em></strong></p><p><strong>(a)</strong>(i) Free education at all levels for all citizens of Nigeria with effect from October 1, 1979.</p><p>(ii) Integrated rural development</p><p>(iii) Provision of health facilities for all the citizens.</p><p>(iv) Full and gainful employment for all citizens.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) The party won Governorship election in five States in 1979, namely, Lagos, Ondo, Bendel, Oyo and Ogun States.</p><p>(ii) The party won seats into the Senate and house of Representatives at the center in 1979 and 1983.</p><p>(iii) The party provided free education in the States it controlled.</p><p>(iv) It implemented free medical facilities in all the states controlled by the party.</p><p>(v) The party acted as a strong opposition to the ruling party, NPN in 1979 and in 1983.</p><p>(vi) The party promoted fiscal discipline in all the States it controlled.</p><p>(vii) The party increased political consciousness through its programmes and campaigns.</p><p>(viii) it was the first party to announce its existence after the lifting of ban on political activities in 1978.</p><p>(ix) It won the Gubernatorial election in Kwara State in 1983. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p> Outline six factors that led to the formation of federalism in Nigeria.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>The factors that led to the formation of Federalism in Nigeria are:</strong></em></p><p>(i) The amalgamation of the North and South in 1914 laid historical foundation for Federalism in Nigeria.</p><p>(ii) The large size of the country.</p><p>(iii) Diversity in culture and ethnic composition.</p><p>(iv) Geographical contiguity: The ethnic groups are geographically contiguous or very close to each other.</p><p>(v) The need to protect minority groups interests.</p><p>(vi) The threat of Northern region to secede from Nigerian in 1953.</p><p>(vii) Nigeria has a large population</p><p>(viii) Outcome of constitutional conferences: The 1953 and 1954 constitutional conferences agreed to establish the Federal system of government in Nigeria.</p><p>(ix) The British intervention: The British government promptly intervened in the political impasse of 1953 which brought the Secretary of State for the colonies to come and preside over the constitutional conference of 1954 in Lagos. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p> (a) What is Foreign Policy?</p><p>(b) Identify five factors that influence Nigeria's foreign policy.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> Foreign Policy is the pattern of behaviour that a nation adopts towards other countries in pursuing its interest in relation with other States, it is a set of guiding principle or action by one State in relation to others.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) An important factor in the foreign policy of Nigeria is its geographical location.</p><p>(ii) Population/size: The population and size of Nigeria have also affected the shaping of Nigeria's foreign policy.</p><p>(iii) Economic resources: The relative resources help Nigeria to champion other African States.</p><p>(iv) The quality of Nigerian leaders: The ability of the leaders can determine the interaction of Nigeria with other nations.</p><p>(v) African interest: With Africa as the center-piece of Nigeria foreign policy, she has been very active in the protection of African interests.</p><p>(vi) Historical factors, such as, Nigeria's attachment to Britain and former British colonies.</p><p>(vii) Democratic consideration affects Nigeria's foreign policy.</p><p>(viii) The relative military strength of Nigeria shapes her relations with other nations.</p><p>(ix) Critical public opinion can shape Nigeria's foreign policy.</p><p>(x) The national interest of Nigeria.</p><p>(xi) The ideological perception of the government e.g. Non-alignment.</p><p>(xii) Membership of international organizations e.g. ECOWAS, UNO, etc. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2007,
        "question": "<p>(a) Describe the origin of the Commonwealth.</p><p>(b) Identify four benefits derived by being a member of the Commonwealth</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> Commonwealth means association of former colonies of Britain.</p><p>(i) The origin of Commonwealth could be traced to 1907 when the representatives of governments of these five countries, Australia, Canada, Ireland, New Zealand and South Africa met for the first time.</p><p>(ii) The Association was formerly known as British Commonwealth of Nations.</p><p>(iii) The modern Commonwealth begin in 1931 when British parliament created Statute of West Minister.</p><p>(iv) Commonwealth is composed of 54 countries now.</p><p>(v) The British Monarch was/still the Head of the Commonwealth.</p><p>(vii) The headquarters of the Commonwealth was /still in London.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) Common language: All the member nations of the Commonwealth adopt English language as their official language.</p><p>(ii) Common legal system: They all derive their legal system from that of the British.</p><p>(iii) Commonwealth scholarship scheme to deserving students.</p><p>(iv) Member countries can borrow money from other countries for their development programmes.</p><p>(v) Trade: The commonwealth members States used to trade with one another on favourable terms.</p><p>(vi) Commonwealth sports: All the commonwealth nations meet every four years for sporting activities.</p><p>(vii) Technical, scientific and educational benefits: Experts in various fields are exchanged among Commonwealth members.</p><p>(viii) Defence: Training of defence personnel in other military academy e.g. Britain, India. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]